Aamer Mohammed

Engineering Leader

**** +91-9985554340

@ aamermail@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/aamer-mohammed

Hyderabad, India

SUMMARY

Experienced leader with a demonstrated history of working and delivering impact in scaling platforms and organizations. Proven track record of success in building and managing high-performing teams, developing and executing engineering practices and driving growth.

EXPERIENCE

Tech Principal | Engineering Leader

Lenovo (on behalf of Thoughtworks)

2023 - Present

Hyderabad, India

Led product innovation, account expansion and stakeholder management

- Guided multiple development streams, ensuring that all teams adhere to established code quality standards, architectural guidelines and innovative software practices
- Interaction with business on product roadmap / product management and CXO level stakeholders on account progress and future initiatives
- Hiring, career progression and performance evaluation of the team
- Tech stack and Tools Java, Spring Boot, React Native, React, AWS, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Datadog
- Patterns and Processes Agile, DevSecOps, BFF, REST

Tech Principal | Engineering Leader

Gap (on behalf of Thoughtworks)

= 2020 - 2023 Hyderabad, India

Led platform modernization, account expansion and stakeholder management

- Modernized 6+ legacy applications to Microservice Architecture which reduced infrastructure cost ~ 20%, response time equivalent to 20% and increased availability of 99.99%
- Interaction with business on product roadmap / product management and CXO level stakeholders on account progress and future initiatives
- Hiring, career progression and performance evaluation of the team. Grew account from 30 members to 55 member team
- Tech stack and Tools Java, Spring Boot, Kafka, Oracle, NoSQL(Cosmos DB), Jenkins, Cucumber, JMeter, Apigee, PCF, Azure, Redis, Spring WebFlux, New Relic, Splunk, Grafana, PagerDuty
- Patterns and Processes Agile, DevSecOps, Strangler Fig pattern, CDC, Event Sourcing, ACL, REST

Technical Lead

DBS Bank (on behalf of Thoughtworks)

Led product development and process improvement

- Led a team to develop travel marketplace by integrating Sabre (one of the world's top GDS) and SQ airlines by following microservice oriented architecture. Developed housing marketplace using serverless architecture
- Hiring, career progression and performance evaluation of the team
- Tech stack Java, Spring Boot, Node.js, AWS, Docker, GraphQL, Redis, Elasticsearch, React, Jenkins

Technical Lead

BMW Group (on behalf of Thoughtworks)

= 2018 - 2019 Munich, Germany

Led platform development and stakeholder management

- Achieved a successful launch of developer platform and personal portal by leading a team of 12 using Agile methodologies
- Interaction with business on product roadmap / product management
- Tech stack Java, Springboot, AWS, Docker, React, Splunk, CircleCI, Terraform, Kubernetes

STRENGTHS



Technical Vision

Architected and built highly scalable distributed systems which resulted in increased client confidence and bringing more revenue to organization



Building High Performing Teams

Built and led self-sufficient and highly skilled teams for multiple clients and delivered high quality solutions which led to increase in account growth



Engineering Practices

Seasoned practitioner in implementing effective development practices resulting in increased developer productivity and client satisfaction

SKILLS

Technical Leadership Team Leadership

Engineering Practices

Distributed Systems

Agile Methodologies

KEY ACHIEVEMENTS



Platform Modernization

Spearheaded the client modernization journey which resulted in faster go-live to market and increased revenue to client and account expansion for our organization



Operational Efficiency

Implemented an account-wide efficiency program that resulted in faster onboarding with high success rate of the engagement and increased client satisfaction



Team Development

Built high-performing teams of 50+ professionals, achieving a 95% retention rate

CERTIFICATION

Confluent Certified Developer for Apache Kafka Confluent

AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate

AWS

SCWCD

Sun Microsystems

EXPERIENCE

Lead Consultant

Neiman Marcus Group (on behalf of Thoughtworks)

🗰 2017 - 2018 👂 Dallas, Texas

Led digital transformation and process improvement

- Led a team to revamp the existing legacy architecture to a cloud native stack which resulted in high availability and increased revenue to client. Revenue increased by 20% after this modernization efforts!
- Tech stack Java, Spring Boot, AWS, Docker, Cassandra, Elasticsearch, React, AppDynamics, Splunk, Jenkins

Lead Consultant

MSF OCA (on behalf of Thoughtworks)

Contribute to betterment of society by building efficient health software

- Made significant contributions in DHIS2 open source software for collecting and storing health data
- Tech stack Java, Spring, PostgreSQL, React, Jenkins, Python, Django

Senior Applications Engineer

- Experience in developing and supporting Oracle Self-Service (SSHR) which is one of the core employee modules in Oracle HRMS
- Developed functional and technical designs and coded 2 key modules (absence, line of reports)

Member Of Technical Staff

- Achieved director-level recognition at ADP by optimizing invoice processing, impacting over 1000 clients by developing the e-imaging process.
- Developed a J2EE web application for handling the details of the ADP associates wherein the users update the details themselves without any admin intervention. It has extensive features and functionalities to track the updates of the users and generate reports.
- Developed a package for ETL operation of vendor files and to regenerate the data from these files by parsing them appropriately into the desired format using SSIS.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Engineering - BE, Computer Science Engineering

University College of Engineering, Osmania University

CERTIFICATION

SC.IP

Sun Microsystems

MY LIFE PHILOSOPHY

Successful teams build great products and successful organizations, not vice versa.

Self

Success is the sum of small efforts, repeated day in and day out.

Robert Collier

Time is Money!

Unknown

Life is 10% of what happens to us and 90% of how we react to it.

Charles R. Swindoll